Hey everybody, welcome
to the content video
going over section 2.4
and 2.5 of your textbooks.
Textbook 1, sorry.
Print function and strings
and also triple quote strings.
So the print function,
as it says here, is
something that will print
out a string, which is a
sequence of characters
enclosed in single quotes.
And here in our textbook,
you can see that
it doesn't display the string's quotes,
but we'll talk about how to do
that in a second and so when we
say print we really just mean
output that string to the console
and there's a lot of different
ways that we can do it
there's a lot of different
variables that we can print out and
it'll print out the value of the
variables but let's jump over
into VS Code and take a look at
what we want to print here and
and we'll do some examples together
so uh let's see print function
and strings okay so let's say
we've got a variable called page
we'll set it equal to 98 something
really fun you're all looking
forward to being 98 and let's go
ahead and print out um a comma
separated list So what I'm going
to do here is I'm just going to say
comma separated items for lack of
a confusion. Okay, so what we're
going to do is I'm actually going
to put in two items into my print
function. I'm going to put a
string, and I'm going to say age.
And that's the first thing. So you
can see if I was to just print out
age, everything within my quotation
marks is going to get printed
out to the console. so here is age
and it's just kind of like this empty
string if you will it's it's not
empty but all that we're seeing is
agee colon space so then what i'm
going to do is i'm going to put a
comma in here and then i'm going
to throw my variable in there age
and print out that to the print that
out to the console now you can see
that we've got age and the variable
um there's a lot of different
things that we can print but let's
jump down to some escape characters
and what I mean by escape
characters are these are things that
in Python can help us
to format our strings a
little bit better or a
little bit differently So let
me print out a string.
I'm going to say, oops,
print, welcome to Python. And if
we were to print this out, we would
see it appear exactly as it is in
the console. So welcome to Python.
Let me throw in a couple of
characters. First, what I'm going
to do is a new line character.
See how that is orange right
here. So I'm going to put a
new line character before two.
and then Python let's do a new line
character let's do two new line
characters and print that out and
we'll see what the difference is
so you can see welcome is on one
line and then the new line character
before two push it onto a new line
and then two new line characters
pushed Python down to two or two
two new lines there's also the
tab character which indents it
and there's a couple of there's a
couple more but new line and tab
are kind of the most important ones
um if we wanted to this is
kind of a cool one print the
results of an expression we
can do that in a print function
so let's say I wanted to
say uh sum of five and three
then I can just add 3 and
5 together right here and
print that out, which is
8. So that is working well.
And that's kind of all
I wanted to talk about
with the print function.
So let's jump to triple
quote strings because
these kind of go together.
And ironically, I'm using them to
write out this section header,
triple quote string. So anything
that's in a triple quote string
won't show up in your output at all.
So, well, sort of. So like if I
run my code, anything that's in
a triple quote string won't be
taken into account when your code
runs. So that's why I use them as
headers, because they format nicely
at the top of my code, and
they don't impact anything that
happens in the algorithms or in the
code as it's running. so it's also
really good for including quotation
marks in actual strings so
let's say that I had a quote this
is a variable and the quote is
I'm terrible at thinking of things
on the spot the quote is it's
nice and sunny today and And then
I wanted to print out a sentence,
my instructor said, actually, I
don't know why I made that a quote.
It's fine.
My instructor said,
quote,
it's nice and sunny today,
which made me mad. I don't know.
So if I try to run this code, you
probably can already tell it's
going to break and it's going to
break for so many reasons. But
part of the reason is because we've
got a double quotation here that
matches this one and then we
have a single quotation and then
another double and then another
double. So Python doesn't know what's
inside of the sequence of characters
that it would designate as
a string and what's not. And so
this would be a good instance where
we could use triple quote strings
to surround the entire thing.
And then if we print this out, you
can see that we have all of those
different things, all those different
quotation marks and apostrophes,
and they're all working just fine.
And so that's one of the advantages
of using triple quote strings in
your code is that it will capture
an entire string or an entire
sequence of characters and it won't
disrupt them at all. and it won't
you know any like if we had like a
like a new line in here or something
it would keep that and it would it
just keeps the formatting really
really nice so I think that's
everything for this content video let
me just check my notes really quick
yeah there's a couple different
ways that we can include quotation
marks in strings but the triple quote
strings is going to be your easiest
and most straightforward one more
thing that was in my notes, sorry,
is a double or single quotation
mark. So let's say I've got a string
and my string is my name. So I'm
just going to type in Chelsea.
Here's, you know, this is okay to
use a double quotation mark string
or it's okay to use a single
quotation mark to designate string
but what's not okay is if you try
to use a single quotation mark and
a double quotation mark this is
when python kind of breaks so you
have to choose one or the other
you can use them interchangeably in
code so like you can see i've got
double quotation mark string here
triple quotation mark string here
and then single quotation mark
string here and they all work just
fine so you just can't intermix
them in a single string so that's
everything for this content video.